For most of history, people hand-picked
wild blueberries. The Passamaquoddy Wild
Blueberry Company, one of the largest
tribe-owned farms in America, employs
150 hand harvesters.
>> It's pretty hard, especially, you know,
when you don't have many much of your
meniscus left.
>> [laughter]
>> Jim Young has been harvesting these
barrens for the last 50 years.
>> I see some muscle. You got some muscles
there.
>> Yeah, man. It's hard.
When we went back to school, we'd be
like solid.
Nobody bothered you in school.
>> Rakers like Jim come from across Maine
and Eastern Canada for the month-long
season, usually beginning in late July.
>> I drive a school bus. And when I'm down
here,
man, it's a lot different than driving a
school bus.
>> [laughter]
>> The Passamaquoddy Wild Blueberry Company
pays each picker $2.75 a box.
A good raker can fill 120 of them a day,
which comes out to $330.
But, this is a dying art form.
All of the state's wild berries used to
be harvested this way. Now, only 10%
are.
>> I think someday this will be gone.
Going to be replaced by machinery.
>> Today, hand harvesters largely operate
where it's too hilly or rocky for big
machines.
>> A million-dollar tractor
tumbling down the hillside, that doesn't
work very well. [music]
>> Over in the flatter areas, machines
scoop up berries by the row.
Most of these mechanical harvesters and
their parts come from Canada.
But, in June 2025, the Trump
administration imposed 50% tariffs on
Canadian steel and aluminum right before
the start of the wild blueberry season.
>> We rely on very few manufacturers for
the equipment we need, and that makes us
particularly [music] vulnerable.
>> That's Eric Venturini, the executive
director of the Wild Blueberry
Commission of Maine.
>> For a while, they couldn't get any
parts.
Manufacturers just decided they weren't
going to ship them at all. If that
machine breaks down during the season,
[music]
you're out of luck.
>> In late 2025, Senator Susan Collins
asked the Trump administration for
emergency funding.
>> To my knowledge, there has not been any
response, [music]
unfortunately, to the letter about
tariffs specifically.